Routine monthly monitoring of insurance books of business is a critical but repetitive risk-management process.
Actuaries and analysts must manually load transactional aggregates, compute key metrics, detect anomalies, decompose them by concentration drivers, and compile explanatory reports.
Traditional business intelligence dashboards visualize these trends, but they stop at charts.
They do not write the explanation or perform the initial triage, creating a time-consuming bottleneck for risk teams.
This workflow is highly suited to an agentic approach because it is multi-step, reasoning-driven, and requires strict security checks.
A simple static script cannot dynamically decide how to triage issues.
Our agent validates input schema quality, runs safety scans, identifies anomalies, selects the correct driver slicing tools, and compiles findings.
To guarantee absolute mathematical correctness, we use a tool-first architecture where deterministic Python
tools compute all metrics, and the LLM is restricted only to narrative synthesis.
The agent's architecture consists of five modular layers.
First, a data layer that ingests synthetic CSV aggregations.
Second, a security layer that checks paths and text notes for prompt injections.
Third, a deterministic tool layer that calculates premiums, loss ratios, and written-premium-weighted averages for rate changes, retention, and benchmark adequacy.
Fourth, an agent reasoning layer that manages Gemini calls and structured schemas.
And fifth, an output layer writing a markdown review memo and a complete JSON trace file.
Let's look at the pipeline in action.
We run the orchestrator tool on a synthetic dataset containing a planted anomaly in the Public D&O segment.
The tool validates the columns, calculates metrics, and triggers two high-severity flags: the loss ratio
rose from fifty percent to eighty-five percent, and claim count nearly tripled, from one to three.
The agent immediately calls the driver investigation tool to slice each anomaly by available dimensions.
The mathematical breakdown shows that both anomalies are entirely concentrated in state New York for the two thousand twenty-five policy year.
In the compiled report, we see the executive summary, metrics tables, concentration drivers, actuary-facing
recommended follow-up questions, and the human review gate flag set to required due to severity.
A full trace JSON is saved for auditability.
Security and privacy are vital.
The security layer blocks path traversals and screens note fields for prompt-injection attacks.
In our test suite, we run deterministic tests to match metric and driver math against YAML expectations.
We also run evaluation cases validating CSV checks, prompt injections, secret disclosure requests, and report quality criteria.
Our full pytest suite of fifty-nine tests passes successfully.
The Actuarial Portfolio Monitoring Agent is not a replacement for professional actuarial opinion or underwriting authority.
Instead, it serves as a robust triage assistant that makes routine reviews faster, safer, and thoroughly documented.
For future work, we plan to transition from flat CSVs to running direct BigQuery analytical queries, GKE-run containerized scheduling, and email alerts.
Thank you.