Routine monthly monitoring of insurance books of business is a critical but repetitive risk-management process.
Actuaries and analysts must manually load transactional aggregates, compute key metrics, detect anomalies,
decompose them by concentration drivers, and compile explanatory reports.
Traditional dashboards visualize these trends, but they stop at charts and do not write explanations.
This workflow is highly suited to an agentic approach because it is multi-step, reasoning-driven, and secure.
Our agent validates input schema quality, runs safety scans, identifies anomalies, and selects driver slicing tools.
To guarantee mathematical correctness, we use a tool-first architecture where deterministic Python tools compute metrics,
and the LLM is strictly restricted only to narrative review synthesis.
The agent's architecture consists of five modular layers: first, a data layer that ingests synthetic CSV aggregations.
Second, a security layer that checks paths and text notes. Third, a deterministic tool layer for metrics calculations.
Fourth, an agent reasoning layer that manages Gemini calls. And fifth, an output layer writing report and trace files.
Let's look at the pipeline in action. We run the orchestrator tool on a synthetic dataset with a loss ratio spike.
The tool validates the columns, calculates metrics, and triggers a high-severity flag because the loss ratio rose to 85%.
The agent immediately calls the driver investigation tool to slice the segment by available dimensions.
The mathematical breakdown shows that this spike is entirely concentrated in state New York for the 2025 policy year.
In the compiled report, we see the executive summary, metrics tables, NY drivers, and actuarial recommended questions.
The human review gate flag is set to required due to severity. A full trace JSON is saved for auditability.
Security and privacy are vital. The security layer blocks path traversals and screens note fields for prompt-injection attacks.
In our test suite, we run deterministic tests to match metric and driver math against YAML expectations.
We also run evaluation cases simulating malformed CSVs, notes prompt injections, and secret disclosure requests.
Our pytest suite verifies all twenty-five tests pass. Additionally, we run a Gate 5 rebuild test from specs alone.
The Actuarial Portfolio Monitoring Agent is not a replacement for professional actuarial opinion or underwriting authority.
Instead, it serves as a robust triage assistant that makes routine reviews faster, safer, and thoroughly documented.
For future work, we plan to transition to direct BigQuery analytical queries, containerized scheduling, and email alerts. Thank you.